Padover, Saul K.; Papers ger010
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Saul K. Padover Papers
1947-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger010
0.2 cubic ft.
This very small collection consists of Saul Padover's writings, course materials, and research materials. Padover was an Austrian-American political scientist, scholar of Soviet propaganda and American foreign policy, and professor at the New School for Social Research.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The documents in this collection were originally housed in a folder inserted into the files of the American Council for Emigres in the Professions (ACEP), which the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives photocopied for preservation purposes in 1974. This folder was evidently the creation and personal property of Saul K. Padover and was thus separated from the ACEP collection.
Biographical History
Saul Kussiel Padover was born in Vienna, Austria, on April 13, 1905. At the age of fifteen, he came to the United States with his father Keva Padover, an American citizen, and mother Frumet Goldmann Padover. He received an A.B. from Wayne State University in Detroit in 1928. He took graduate courses at Yale University in 1928-1929 and went on to receive an A.M. (1930) and Ph.D. (1932) in history from the University of Chicago. After taking research positions at the University of Chicago (1932) and the University of California (1933-36), he worked at a number of posts in the U.S. Department of the Interior (1938-1944). He then served as a London-based political analyst for the Federal Communications Commission (1944) and as an intelligence officer for the Office of Strategic Services (1944) and the U.S. Army (1944-1946). After working as an editorial writer (1946-1948) for PM, a left-leaning and short-lived New York City newspaper, he joined the Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research (1949) and taught political science. He remained an active member of the faculty until his death in 1981.
Padover wrote or edited books about many eminent American and European political figures, among them Alexander Hamilton, Thomas Jefferson, Joseph II of Austria, Louis XVI of France, James Madison, and Karl Marx. He also wrote several books about twentieth-century American and European politics, a memoir of his experiences as an intelligence officer, and several works on foreign policy. A liberal anti-communist, he asserted in the 1950s that the Soviet Union was a serious threat and should be treated as such.
Toward the end of his life, Padover contemplated writing a book about the American Council for Emigres in the Professions (ACEP), an organization established to help refugees fleeing Nazi Germany and Austria. To that end, Padover secured physical possession of the ACEP files and housed them in his New School office. Padover passed away on February 22, 1981, in New York City, before he could complete this project.
Scope and Contents
The materials in this collection were originally housed in a folder labeled "Foreign Affairs" that was inadvertently inserted into the files of the American Council for Emigres in the Professions (ACEP), which were sent to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 1974. Saul Kussiel Padover, who kept the ACEP files in his office at the New School for Social Research, apparently created and misfiled this folder. The ACEP files were sent to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, which photocopied them for preservation purposes. The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, which sent the ACEP files to the Immigration History Research Center at the University of Minnesota after photocopying, retained possession of Padover's "Foreign Affairs" folder.
Owing to its origins, this collection is limited in scope. Scholars seeking information about Padover's early life, his work as a journalist, or his writings on Alexander Hamilton, Thomas Jefferson, Karl Marx, and other political figures will find little of interest in it. However, those searching for materials that illuminate his attitude toward the Soviet Union and the Cold War and that document his work as a faculty member of the New School for Social Research will find it useful.
The collection contains seven typescript scholarly articles and two typescript fragments of longer articles. Eight were written in the fifteen years following the end of the Second World War. The ninth may have been written circa 1970; however, it may have been written in the 1950s and revised in 1964, 1970, and 1972. These articles document Padover's staunch anti-communist views and his interest in the relationship between American public opinion and American foreign policy. Several articles also discuss some of his work as an intelligence officer during the Second World War.
The collection also contains syllabi, student-written presentation outlines, and lecture notes that were generated between 1955 and 1970 and shed light upon Padover's work in the classroom. Materials that Padover prepared while leading the General Seminar, the New School's ongoing interdisciplinary seminar for faculty members, help to document his own activities and the workings of the General Seminar itself.
Other materials in the collection consist of assorted documents that Padover found relevant to his academic work. Of particular note is a May 3, 1972 circular letter from New School President John R. Everett concerning student protests against the Vietnam War.
Whenever possible, the original order of the papers was preserved. However, many of the documents were in substantial disarray (e.g., portions of a single typescript were scattered throughout the folder). As a result, much of the material was rearranged to facilitate its use. Several newspaper clippings were photocopied for preservation purposes.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has three series, arranged chronologically.
Series 1 - Scholarly Writings, 1947-1970
Series 2 - Course Materials, 1955-1970
Series 3 - Research Materials, 1947-1972
Political Science; Propaganda, Russian.; Political scientists -- United States.; Austrians -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century.; Padover, Saul Kussiel, 1905-1981; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.)
- Scholarly Writings, 1947-1970; 1; 0.07 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of nine typescript essays (two of which are fragments) concerning Soviet propaganda initiatives, American efforts to counter it, the influence of public opinion on American foreign policy, and notes on related topics. One of these essays appeared in published form in Psychological Warfare, a pamphlet published by the Foreign Policy Association in 1951. Other essays in this series may also have been published. Also included in this series are notes that Padover wrote while working on these essays. Almost all of the materials in this series were written in the late 1940s and early 1950s, but the last essay in the series may have been revised in 1964, 1970, and 1972. As a result, it has been dated circa1970.
  - Soviet Propaganda Themes Against the U.S. (unpub. TS), and Notes, 1947-1948 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 1)
  - Fragment, "Psychological Warfare" (unpub. TS), and Notes, ca. 1951 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 2)
  - Psychological Warfare (unpub. TS), 1952 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 3)
  - Psychological Warfare (unpub. TS), 1953 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 4)
  - American Opinion in an Age of World Revolution (unpub. TS), 1953 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 5)
  - The Age of Stalin? (unpub. TS), 1953 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 6)
  - The Soviet Propaganda Apparatus (unpub. TS), ca. 1953 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 7)
  - Fragment on Communist Propaganda in the Philippines (unpub. TS), ca. 1955 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 8)
  - Notes on New York Times Article, 1956 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 9)
  - Fragment, "Foreign Policy and Public Opinion" (unpub. TS), ca. 1970 (Box 1 (1-Scholarly Writings), Folder 10)
- Course Materials, 1955-1970; 2; 0.1 cubic ft.
  This series contains assorted materials generated in connection with Padover's teaching activities. Included are syllabi for a number of graduate and undergraduate courses, lecture notes, outlines of and notes about student presentations on various aspects of American foreign policy, and materials Padover created when leading the New School's General Seminar for faculty members.
  - Syllabus, "Basic Factors in World Politics", 1955 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 11)
  - Stock Price List and Notes on Total War and on U.S. Foreign Policy, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1967 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 13)
  - Notes on U.S. Troops Abroad and Clipping on Pakistan, 1967 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 14)
  - Wells, "[Suez Crisis] Chronology" (unpub. TS), 1967 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 15)
  - Syllabus, "The Noble Tradition: Men Who Made American Democracy", 1969 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 16)
  - List of [Presentation] Topics, "American Foreign Policy" Course, 1969 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 17)
  - Smith, "American Foreign Policy: The Purchase of the Virgin Islands" (unpub. TS), and Maps, 1969 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 18)
  - Notes on Kramm Presentation, "Lend-Lease," and on Smith Presentation, "V.I. Acquisition", 1969 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 19)
  - Syllabus, "American Foreign Policy", 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 20)
  - Notes on U.S. Foreign Policy, ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 21)
  - Fast, "U.S.-Philippine Relations 1945-1947" (unpub. TS), ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 22)
  - Tortorella, "Dwight D. Eisenhower and His Concept of the Presidency" (unpub. TS), ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 23)
  - General Seminar syllabus, "American Foreign Policy: Case Studies", ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 24)
  - Definitions (unpub. TS), ca. 1970 (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 25)
  - Notes on the Nature of Power and on the Philippines, Undated (Box 1 (2-Course Materials), Folder 26)
- Research Materials, 1947-1972; 3; 0.03 cubic ft.
  This series consists of materials that Padover collected for their informational value: a United Nations Information Service flier, newspaper clippings about the Voice of America and foreign policy expert George F. Kennan, an article concerning the U.S. Supreme Court's refusal to hear a case concerning the constitutionality of American involvement in Vietnam, and a letter from the President of the New School concerning protests against the Vietnam War.
  - United Nations Information Service, News Brief, 1947 (Box 1 (3-Research Materials), Folder 27)
  - Clippings on Voice of America and George F. Kennan, 1956 (Box 1 (3-Research Materials), Folder 28)
  - Court Rejects Case Concerning the Legality of the War (pub.), 1967 (Box 1 (3-Research Materials), Folder 29)
  - Letter from New School President Concerning Vietnam War Protests, 1972 (Box 1 (3-Research Materials), Folder 30)